Hi, everyone. This is
the question review for
antiarrhythmics. A research study
was investigating new agents
for preventing recurrent
supraventricular arrhythmias.
After administering the
agent to healthy volunteers,
serum studies revealed the
appearance of antinuclear
and antihistone antibodies.
which of these drugs
is most likely to induce
the same antibody response
so this is saying that
whatever drug was given
is showing a pattern of drug
-induced lupus and looking
at the choices we
know that there is one
antiarrhythmic that has an
acetylation metabolism pathway
And its metabolite, if
you are a slow acetylator,
can induce arthralgia
and the formation of
the butterfly rash. And
that metabolite is known
as N-acetylprocanamide.
So in this question,
we can say procanamide
is the best answer.
Procainamide and
quinidine are 1A
antiarrhythmics that
block the sodium channel.
So they somewhat
prolong depolarization,
but they also prolong
the action potential
because they block
potassium channels.
So these two can show
an increase in QT.
They can also raise QRS. and
they're also
muscarinic blockers.
Quinidine will also have
the synchonism effect.
Amiodarone is the class
3 and this is the one
that can also prolong
the action potential,
has no effect on depolarization
and can exhibit hepatotoxicity,
corneal deposits, smurf skin,
changes in thyroid panel,
and, of course,
pulmonary fibrosis.
Flecanide is 1C.
Not much happening with the
action potential, but it
does significantly prolong
repolarization. So you'll
see that the QRS will be
significantly higher with
this one, and that can
increase the ventricular rate.
Lidocaine is 1B. It
works on depolarized
tissue. It lowers the
QT, so it is appropriate
to prevent ventricular
events after an MI.
And then metoprolol
is selective beta-1.
It's an AV node
suppressant. Okay, and so AV
block can be an adverse
effect of metoprolol.
So in this question,
E is the best answer.
Now,
somebody is 59 years old, has
a history of hypertension,
brought to the ED
with chest pain,
and diagnosed with
an inferior MI.
Minutes later, he
is unresponsive.
He is in V-fib and CPR
is initiated, and he
remains in V-fib. He is
given a medication that
decreases the myocardial
action potential duration
and also decreases
the refractory period.
Which of the following can
be expected at higher doses?
So what's the clue
here is the post-MI
and this medication
should have been
considered to prevent
the ventricular event.
And we know that this
drug is going to reduce
action potential
duration, so decrease QT.
The third clue is the
fact that whatever he
was given, what's the
adverse effect? So
this is very simply
without prolonging it,
is lidocaine.
And the biggest clue
is the reduction
in action potential duration.
So looking at the choices,
bronchospasm, I would say no.
This would probably be
best for maybe a non
-selective beta blocker
or even adenosine.
Bleeding can be from
thrombocytopenia that
can happen with
quinidine. It can be
from anticoagulants
or antiplatelet drugs.
Butterfly rash is
what we saw in the
previous question that
would be best associated
with procainamide
or even hydralazine.
Neutropenia from a previous
lecture, that would
be an ADP receptor
blocker like tyclopidine.
That's the specific one.
And then paresthesia
would be the best
answer. Because we know
that with lidocaine,
being an anesthetic, it's
an amide anesthetic, Giving
it too much can cause
neurological symptoms,
whether it be paresthesia
or, in worst case scenario,
a seizure.
So in this question, this
applies to lidocaine, reducing
the QT post-MI to prevent
the ventricular events.
And you need to be
mindful with injecting
it because you can get
neurological events.
so again not to go through
this a hundred times
but we did quinidine
and procainamide and
disopiramide is the one with
the most muscarinic receptor
block of the three so
if you give disopiramide
it is suggested that
you give an AV node
suppressant to protect
the ventricles So giving
something like a beta
blocker would be appropriate.
And as you can see
here, you're getting
prolongation of the
action potential.
And that has to do with
potassium channel blockade.
And then the 1B, again,
the thing to note is that
not much is happening with
depolarization because
it's working on those tissues
that have been depolarized.
But the lowering of
the QT is what helps
prevent ventricular events
in those patients post-MI.
And then 1C, not much
is happening here
with the action
potential duration,
but there is
significant prolongation
of depolarization,
which is significantly
raising QRS and the
ventricular rate.
A 47-year-old male
brought to the ED with
sudden onset
palpitations and dyspnea.
The EKG revealed AFib.
First-line therapy was not
effective. He was
given dofidolide.
Where in this diagram
does dofidolide work?
So dofidolide is considered
to be a potassium
channel blocker. This is
one that is going to slow
repolarization and the reason
why it wouldn't be first
line is because that slow
rate of repolarization
is going to have a
significant effect at raising
the QT. So when you are given
dofidolide or abutilide,
most likely you have
to remain in a clinical
setting so they can review
your EKG over 4 hours.
So where is
repolarization happening?
It's going to happen here at 3.
Okay, so we could
say that the best
answer here is going
to be, of course, D.
If I was talking about
0 to 1, the upstroke, I
probably would say it's
a sodium channel blocker,
especially the 1A and
the 1C, not so much 1B.
Phase 1, nothing
much is happening.
Phase 2 would be the formation
of the shoulder, which
has to do with calcium
entry, so verapamil and
diltiazem could work here
especially if we're talking
about AV node suppression
and the pacemaker and then
4 again we're thinking
about lowering the slope
here and that could be
achieved with beta blockers
especially if we're talking
about again the pacemaker
or the SA node and even
verapamil and diltiazem but
for this one it's going to
be D the best answer So,
an 87-year-old suffered
an acute ST elevation
MI, and he was
treated with aspirin,
metoprolol, and heparin,
and he is transported to
the cath lab, and he
becomes unresponsive.
He receives defibrillation
and CPR and epineprin
and does not convert
to a sinus rhythm.
He's given an
antiarrhythmic that can
cause changes in
the thyroid panel.
Which of the following
adverse effects is most
associated with long
-term use of this agent?
So what stands out
is that this drug
is going to affect
his thyroid panel.
So that hopefully is
pointing to amiodarone. now
the next step is pretty
much asking you what's
another adverse effect of
amiodarone is it bleeding
no if anything bleeding
can be antiplatelets maybe
quinidine because of
the thrombocytopenia
anticoagulants like heparin
aspirin being a blocker of
thromboxane Is it increased
mortality after an MI?
That might be something
like flecainide,
1C, because those by
significantly prolonging
repolarization, it can
affect the ventricular rate.
Is it pulmonary fibrosis?
Most likely, yes.
Reduced platelets?
Again, that would be
quinidine. and then
the yellow-green vision
would most likely
correspond to digoxin.
So pulmonary fibrosis is,
in fact, the right answer.
Remember, that effect
is mediated by an
immunological reaction where
you're getting hyperplasia
of the type 2
pneumocytes and that's
reducing surfactant
production. And there is also,
with all of this, some
production of ROSs.
So class 3, they
delay repolarization.
Reverse use dependence,
where the action is
happening with these drugs
at a reduced heart rate.
So that would mean that
somebody with a lower
heart rate will be more
prone to elevated QT.
and again since it's iodinated
not only are we changing
the thyroid panel because
we might be making more
hormone with more iodine
there's also a inhibition of t4
to t3 conversion and that
can lead to hypothyroidism
the drug has a long half
-life it's going to affect the
liver affects fatty acid
oxidation there. It's going
to cause discoloration of
the skin, corneal deposits,
and of course, you
need to be mindful
of drug interactions
with amiodarone.
This 53-year-old
male with AFib,
hyperlipidemia, and
COPD presented for
his annual exam. He's
taking lovastatin,
sodalol, and inhaled
tyotropium to manage
his condition.
Tyotropium, like the name
shows, is a muscarinic
blocker like atropine.
And muscarinic blockers
in the lung can
cause smooth muscle
relaxation. And they're
considered to be the
first line for COPD.
Anyway, he complains
of recent episodes
of wheezing and
coughing, but he
has no fever, so
it's not infectious.
So which describes the
mechanism that has worsened
his respiratory condition?
So we know it can't be
lovastatin, because if
anything, he might have myalgia,
changes in his liver function,
but HMG-CoA reductase
inhibitors do not have
an effect on wheezing.
The tiotropium is
actually a treatment
for COPD as I just mentioned.
So looking at sodalol,
sodalol is a class 3
antiarrhythmic because
it does have some
effect at blocking the
potassium channels and
increasing the action
potential duration.
but still it's a non
-selective beta blocker.
So blocking beta 1 in
the heart will reduce
norepinephrine and cardiac
output and heart rate
but blocking B2 in the
lungs is going to result
in bronchoconstriction.
So most likely his
exacerbation of COPD is
coming from beta blockade.
beta 2 beta 1 would
be helping the heart
beta 2 would be worsening
the lung function
M2 block
remember that's
going to increase
AV node action that's going
to be true of atropine
if we were to use it for
a bradycardic episode
alpha 1 block which you
can see with amiodarone
or even procainamide can
decrease blood pressure.
And then calcium channel
blockers might be effective
for this patient because
they can somewhat
mimic the action of beta
blockers with respect to
reducing SA and AV node
action, but calcium channel
blockers have no effect
on the bronchial smooth
muscle. So the best answer
here is going to be B.
Blocking the beta 2
receptors is exacerbating
this problem with
his lung function.
Okay, so again, when we're
talking about class
2 and class 4,
they're going to decrease
the slope of phase
4. Okay, blocking
adrenergic tone, which is
going to be predominantly
for the pacemaker.
And then the calcium
channel blockers, as
mentioned, are going to
work here at the shoulder.
Okay, similar in action
to the beta blockers. But
remember, the diapenes do
not work for arrhythmias
because the diapenes
are specific for the
smooth muscle of the
arteriole. The concern would
be if we lower blood
pressure through the
baroreceptor reflex mechanism,
you can get reflexive
tachycardia because you're
raising sympathetics.
So that is why we
reserve rapamyl and
diltiazem for these
arrhythmia cases.
Bradycardia makes
sense because you're
lowering the action
in the SA node.
Constipation, you're
blocking calcium in the gut
and you're not allowing for
peristalsis of the food.
And then gingival overgrowth
has to do with the fact
that you're increasing the
production of fibroblasts.
And that's going to
increase collagen deposition
in the mouth. So you're
going to have over time,
especially with, I believe,
verapamil in overgrowth.
So we have an 83-year
-old presenting to the
clinic for follow-up
of his heart failure.
Since his last visit, he
sees yellow, and he's also
experiencing diarrhea and
nausea. If this was due
to a specific drug, which
is a mechanism of action?
So I think what really
stands out aside from
the heart failure is the
yellow and that is known
as xanthopsia and that
has to do with the
fact that the sodium
potassium ATPase is going to
be affected in the
retinal pigmentosa cells.
So that is going to be
one of the early adverse
effects that we do have
with digoxin. So looking at
the mechanism of action,
it is not a beta blocker,
it is not a potassium channel
blocker, or a calcium.
It is an inhibitor of
sodium potassium ATPase.
So this was fairly easy,
and this adverse effect is
sometimes labeled as the
Van Gogh effect of digoxin.
With respect to AB node
suppression and the negative
chronotropic effects,
that's really pointing
to a vagal induced effect
that is parasympathetic.
The thing to know is that
low potassium levels is
going to potentiate the action
of sodium potassium ATPase.
so with respect to the
exchanger more sodium is
staying inside and then
calcium is not getting shuttled
out it stays inside the
myocyte and you're going to
have more calcium for
contraction and that is a
positive inotropic effect but
again hypokalemia what will
happen is after phase four
of the action potential
you're going to get that
delayed after depolarization
Delayed after
depolarization happens post
-iskemia, and it happens
with high calcium
levels, and that is
attributed to digoxin.
Renal impairment,
you need to dose this
medication carefully
in the elderly.
Gynecomastia,
because the backbone
of this medication
is estrogenic.
And then issues
with the GI tract.
Anthacid and cholestyramine
will stop the
absorption of the medication.
So you need to space
these two away from
digoxin by several hours.
Quinidine is going to
affect P-glycoprotein in
the kidney. And if that
is the case, then you're
going to have a reduced
digoxin clearance.
Same thing with rarapamil.
And then lastly,
amiodarone can inhibit
digoxin's metabolism.
In the case of a dig
-induced arrhythmia
or torsades, what
you want to do is to
stop calcium from
coming into the cell.
You want to make sure that
it stays out. And that
will be done with another
ion known as magnesium.
A 20-year-old female
brought to the ED
after experiencing
fatigue and palpitations
had a heart rate of
300 beats per minute.
She's administered a drug which
reduced her heart
rate very quickly,
but later she complains
of tightness in her
chest and difficulty
breathing. Which of the
following was most likely
administered? So by
this question, we know
that she probably has
a PSVT, and she was
likely giving adenosine.
And adenosine works quickly,
has a short half-life,
and it works G-inhibitory.
and what that would mean
is that it's
lowering cyclic AMP
via inhibiting adenyl cyclase
and that's going to lower
the heart rate and the
speed of the impulse
through the AV node but we
know that adenosine has
some G-stimulatory effects
and that's going to
lead to smooth muscle
relaxation and you're going
to get vasodilation and
that could be some
hypotension, some flushing.
And then it has a GQ
mechanism and that's going
to increase IP3 and DAG,
increase calcium, and
that's going to cause
smooth muscle contraction in
the lungs. So, patients
might get a few minutes
of maybe some shortness
of breath or wheezing.
Okay.
Amiodarone,
again,
thyroid, liver,
lung,
eyes, skin.
Diltiazim,
AV node block.
It's negative,
chronotropic. and then
constipation,
gingival hyperplasia.
Disopiramide, if anything,
through the fact that it
blocks the M2 receptors in
the heart, it's going to
increase AV node action. So
you want to give disopiramide
with an AV node blocker.
And then metoprolol,
beta 1 selective, what
I would be most concerned
with is AV block.
So A is in fact the best
answer for this question.
And as I discussed, this is
the opposite of theophylline.
So theophylline is an
adenosine antagonist. So that
would make sense that theophylline
would cause bronchodilation
while adenosine is causing
bronchoconstriction.
In the heart,
adenosine is going to be a
G-inhibitory process, and
it slows things down. If you
overdose on theophylline,
you're switching over to
a G-stimulatory process.
And what makes theophylline
a narrow therapeutic index
drug, and why we don't use
it much anymore, is that
the toxicity on the heart
can result in having an
arrhythmia. okay and again
theobromine is the origin of
theophylline and aminophylline
and those are related to
caffeine so it makes sense
you're thinking about when
you drink lots of caffeine
whether it be tea or coffee
or chocolate some people
are more prone to get
stimulation and they can get
some palpitations. So we will
review that later in both
respiratory and even in GI,
but that's just a
good way to introduce
the topic and to kind of
connect the relationship
between adenosine
and theophylline.
Thank you all for your
attention. If there are
further questions, please
feel free to reach out.
Until then, take care
and I'll see you soon.
Thank you.